CONTACT Information

3438 North Quad University of Michigan Ann Arbor, MI, 48109 yanchenm@umich.edu https://chensivan.github.io/

SHORT BIO.

Yan Chen is a Ph.D. candidate at the University of Michigan School of Information. He studies human-computer interaction (HCI) with a focus on software development tools and collaboration. His work has been published at top HCI conferences, including CHI (x3) and CSCW (x1), and also topic-specific venues like VL/HCC (x2) and ACM IMX (x1). His work has received the best paper award. Yan has also been on the program committee and paper reviewers for many HCI venues. His review has received Excellent Review recognition.

RESEARCH INTERESTS My research in human-computer interaction (HCI) studies challenges that computer programmers at all levels of expertise face when using existing tools and methods to seek support. It combines human and machine computation to create programming support systems that can effectively and scalably assist programmers when needed. The systems I create address challenges including providing within-IDE help in nearly real time, providing feedback to learners at scale, synthesizing code snippets reliably, and testing an interface with high coverage, which neither computers nor humans can effectively solve alone. To make these systems possible, my research explores how to design workflows and interfaces that can effectively coordinate and scale the collective effort of experts, non-experts, and machines.

Keywords: Programmining collaboration, development tools, crowdsourcing.

EDUCATION

University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI, US

Ph.D. in Information Science (2014 - present)

- Advisor: Steve Onev
- Committee: Mark Ackerman, Mark Guzdial, Philip Guo

University of Colorado, Boulder, CO, US

M.S in Applied Mathematics (2013 - 2014)

- Master Thesis: Asymptotic Series Solutions To One-Dimensional Helmholtz Equation
- Thesis Advisor: Harvey Segur

University of Colorado, Boulder, CO, US

B.S. in Applied Mathematics and B.S. in Electrical and Computer Engineering (2011 - 2014)

Professional Experience Google, Mountain View, CA, US

- UX Research Intern, (May. 2019 Aug. 2019)
- Mentors: Dr. Tao Dong Supporting programming learning via live streaming

Snap Inc., Seattle, WA, US

- Research Intern, (Jan. 2018 Apr. 2018)
- Mentors: Dr. Andres Monroy-Hernandez and Dr. Rajan Vaish Interviewed with staffed Snap Story curators on their curation tools experience. Drew design

implications. Developed a hybrid-machine workflow and system for rapid video curation. Conducted a large-scale (30k+ video) study to explore the effectiveness of the approach.

Harvard University, Cambridge, MA, US

- Undergraduate Research Intern, (Jun. 2013 Aug. 2013)
- Advisors: Dr. Katharina Reinecke, Professor Krzysztof Gajos
 Developed a web application that quantifies websites' aesthetics and predicts visual preference
 of people with different cultural background.

University of Colorado, Boulder, CO, US

- Research Assistant, (Sep. 2012 May 2014)
- Advisor: Professor Tom Yeh
 Developed and conducted in-lab experiments for the DARPA active authentication project
 on personal computer and smart phone. Applied image and video processing techniques for
 pattern recognition.

University of Colorado, Boulder, CO, US

- Research Assistant, (Sep. 2012 May 2014)
- Advisor: Professor Harvey Segur
 Generalized hyperasymptotic series mechanism to approximate other functions. Discovered
 unavoidable oscillation in hyperasymptotic series mechanism.

CONFERENCE PAPERS AND JOURNALS

- [8]. Yan Chen, Walter S. Lasecki, and Tao Dong. Towards Supporting Programming Education at Scale via Live Streaming. In *Proceedings of the International ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW 2020)*.
- [7]. Yan Chen, Jaylin Herskovitz, Walter S. Lasecki, and Steve Oney. A Hybrid Crowd-Machine Workflow for Program Synthesis. IEEE Symposium on Visual Languages and Human-Centric Computing VL/HCC '20.
- [6]. Yan Chen, Jaylin Herskovitz, Gabriel Matute, April Wang, Sang Won Lee, Walter S. Lasecki, and Steve Oney. EdCode: Towards Personalized Support at Scale for Remote Assistance in CS Education. IEEE Symposium on Visual Languages and Human-Centric Computing VL/HCC '20.
- [5]. Yan Chen, Maulishree Pandey, Jean Y. Song, Walter S. Lasecki, and Steve Oney. Improving Crowd-Supported GUI Testing with Structural Guidance. In *Proceedings of the International ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2020)*, Hawaii, USA.
- [4]. Yan Chen, Andres Monroy-Hernandez, Ian Wehrman, Steve Oney, Walter S. Lasecki, Rajan Vaish. Sifter: A Hybrid Workflow for Theme-based Video Curation at Scale. In *Proceedings of the International ACM Conference on Interactive Media Experiences (IMX 2020)*, Barcelona, Spain.
- [3]. Yan Chen, Sang Won Lee, Yin Xie, Yiwei Yang, Walter S. Lasecki, Steve Oney. Codeon: On-Demand Software Development Assistance. In *Proceedings of the International ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2017)*, Denver, USA.
- [2]. Yan Chen, Steve Oney, Walter S. Lasecki. Towards Providing On-Demand Expert Support for Software Developers. In *Proceedings of the International ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2016)*, San Jose, USA.
- [1]. Vishal Patel, Tom Yeh, M Salem, Yangmuzi Zhang, Yan Chen, Rama Chellappa, Larry Davis. Screen Fingerprints: a Novel Modality for Active Authentication. *IT Professional* 15, no. 4 (2013):38-42.

OTHER PUBLICATIONS

[9]. Yan Chen, Yaxing Yao, Jasmine Jones. WireOn: Supporting Remote Collaboration for Embedded System Development. Demo at The International ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW 2020).

[8]. Yan Chen, Jasmine Jones, Steve Oney. On-demand Programming Assistance. New Future of Work Symposium at Microsoft Research.

[7].Yan Chen. Mocking-up Desired UI Behaviors from UI Element-Based Recording. Graduate Consortium at *IEEE Symposium on Visual Languages & Human-Centric Computing (VL-HCC'19)*.

[6]. Yan Chen, Steve Oney, and Walter S. Lasecki. Enhancing Context and Guidance for Asynchronous Collaboration. Poster at *Human Computer Interaction Consortium (HCIC'18)*.

[5].Sang Won Lee, **Yan Chen**, and Walter S. Lasecki. Speech-To-Tasks: Real-Time Crowd Generation of Task Lists from Speech. Demo at *The AAAI Conference on Human Computation (HCOMP '17)*.

[4]. Sang Won Lee, **Yan Chen**, Noah Klugman, Sai R. Gouravajhala, Angela Chen, and Walter S. Lasecki. Exploring Coordination Models for Ad Hoc Programming Teams. Late-Breaking-Work at *International ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2017)*, Denver, USA.

[3]. Yan Chen, Steve Oney, Walter S. Lasecki. Expert Crowd Support Systems for Software Developers. Collective Intelligence 2016, New York, USA. (Oral presentation)

[2]. Yan Chen, Steve Oney, Walter S. Lasecki. Automatically Capturing Context to Create Microtasks for Software Development. Workshop at *International ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2016)*, San Jose, USA.

[1].Esther Vasiete, Yan Chen, Ian Char, Tom Yeh, Vishal Patel, Larry Davis, Rama Chellappa. Toward a non-intrusive, physio-behavioral biometric for smartphones. In *Proceedings of the 16th international conference on Human-computer interaction with mobile devices & services.* (MobileHCI 2014), pp. 501-506. Toronto, Canada.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI, US

- Introduction to Programming (with Anthony Whyte), (Fall 2019)
- User Interface Development (with Walter Lasecki), (Winter 2019)
- User Interface Development (with Mark Guzdial), (Fall 2018)
- User Interface Development (with Mark Ackerman), (Fall 2017)
- Introduction to Programming (with Steve Oney and Paul Resnick), (Fall 2016)
- Data Visualization (with Eytan Adar), (Fall 2015)

STUDENTS SUPERVISED

University of Michigan

- Muhan Zhao (Summer 2020 present), undergrad at UMich.
- Yunjie Guo (Summer 2020- present), undergrad at UMich.
- Ruidong Liu (September 2019 December 2019), undergrad at UMich.
- Yiwei Yang (Fall 2015 Spring 2016), now PhD student at UWashington.
- Gabriel Matute (Fall 2016 present), undergrad at UMich.
- Jaylin Herskovitz (Fall 2016 present), now PhD student at UMich.
- Yin Xie (Summer 2016), now interaction designer at Internet Brands.

University of Colorado at Boulder

• Ian Char (Fall 2013 - Spring 2014), now PhD student at CMU.

SERVICE

Paper reviewing

- PC: HCOMP Demo/WiP '17, CHI LBW'19
- Reviewer for CHI '16-'20, UIST '16-'20, CSCW '17-'19

Led "POSSE Workshop: Introduction to Web Programming" (Workshop) @ POSSE Foundation, 2018, Ann Arbor, MI, United States

Michigan Interactive and Social Computing Research Group (MISC) student coordinator ('19)

Honors & Awards

Best paper award, VL/HCC'20.

Special Recognition Received for Excellent Review CHI'19.

Selected as a HCIC-Funded Student in University of Michigan to participate in Human Computer Interaction Consortium(HCIC) 2018 "AI & HCI".

University of Michigan Rackham Graduate School Student Travel Grant ('16, '17, '20)

University of Michigan School of Information Student Travel Grant ('16, '17, '20)

Press

Best practice guidance for live streaming programming, Google (2019)

(youtube: https://bit.ly/36W0Pkg)

Best practices for hosting a live streaming coding session, Google (2019)

(medium: https://bit.ly/2SfEavb)